Guide to the Records and Papers of Terry Sanford, 1945-1998 UA.03.60.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Series 1. Duke University. President Terry Sanford Records, 1969-1985.
  - Subseries 1.2. Speeches, 1970-1985., 5.0 ln. ft (about 150 items (Box 142-145)
    - 1983
      - "Bringing the Fertile Field to a Rich Harvest," July 14, 1983 (Box 144)
      - At Duke Memorial Methodist Church, October 16, 1983 (Box 144)
      - President's Address to the Faculty, October 27, 1983 (Box 144)
      - Education Commission of the States, December 2, 1983 (Box 144)
      - Sandhills Community College, December 2, 1983 (Box 144)
      - 50th- Anniversary Governing Board Meeting, December 5, 1983 (Box 144)
      - "On Doing the Right Thing," December 15, 1983 (Box 144)
    - 1984
      - Carteret County Chamber of Commerce, March 22, 1984 (Box 144)
      - Fayetteville Area Health Education Foundation, June 1984 (Box 144)
      - Charles A. Duke's Memorial Service, December 9, 1984 (Box 144)
      - University of Maryland Commencement, December 21, 1984 (Box 144)
      - "Outrageous Ambitions," To Annual Faculty Meeting, October 25, 1984 (Box 144)
    - 1985
      - To Democratic Congressmen and Senators re Chairmanship of the DNC, January 29, 1985 (Box 144)
      - To the Third World Convocation, February 13, 1985 (Box 144)
      - To Human Relations Commission Banquet, February 26, 1985 (Box 144)
      - Presbyterian College Commencement, May 12, 1985 (Box 144)
    - Letters (Box 145)
    - 1970
      - War in Indochina, May 13, 1970 (Box 145)
      - Yearbook, July 8, 1970 (Box 145)
      - To the Publications Board, Re: Vulgarity, July 9, 1970 (Box 145)
      - On Athletics, August 11, 1970 (Box 145)
      - Handbook, September 17, 1970 (Box 145)
      - University Matters, October 16, 1970 (Box 145)
      - Labor Unions, October 26, 1970 (Box 145)
      - Calendar, December 14, 1970 (Box 145)
    - 1971
      - Tuition, January 11, 1971 (Box 145)
      - Academic Calendar, January 18, 1971 (Box 145)
      - Drug Policy, February 22, 1971 (Box 145)
      - ASDU Letter-Fleishman Announcement, February 25, 1971 (Box 145)
      - Residential Life Committee, March 8, 1971 (Box 145)
      - To Students and Parents on Dormitory Visitation, April 20, 1971 (Box 145)
      - Pye Resignation; Honorary Degrees; Commencement, May 3, 1971 (Box 145)
      - ROTC, September 3, 1971 (Box 145)
      - Fringe Benefits, September 8, 1971 (Box 145)
      - Invitation by Faculty to Freshmen, September 20, 1971 (Box 145)
      - Planning Committee, October 21, 1971 (Box 145)
      - Visitation and Campus Community Council Proposal, November 11, 1971 (Box 145)
    - 1972
      - Affirmative Action, January 1, 1972 (Box 145)
      - Planning Committee, January 7, 1972 (Box 145)
      - National Labor Relations Board Election (Union), January 21, 1972 (Box 145)
      - Social Regulations, March 3, 1972 (Box 145)
      - Archivist for Duke, April 10, 1972 (Box 145)
      - Tuition Increase, June 12, 1972 (Box 145)
      - Bob Entman Political Study, July 1972 (Box 145)
      - David Ross Appointed to Head Capital Campaign, August 24, 1972 (Box 145)
      - Planning Report; Archivist; History of Duke, October 12, 1972 (Box 145)
    - 1973
      - Financial Aid; Phi Beta Kappa; Art Museum; International Scholars, May 1973 (Box 145)
      - Archives, May 1973 (Box 145)
      - Hospital North and Capital Funds Campaign, May 22, 1973 (Box 145)
      - Epoch Campaign, September 27, 1973 (Box 145)
      - Report to the Faculty, October 25, 1973 (Box 145)
      - On Financial Status of Duke, October 25, 1973 (Box 145)
      - Ways to Improve Duke, November 6, 1973 (Box 145)
    - 1974
      - To Alumni (Enclosing copy of NY Times Supplement), January 1974 (Box 145)
      - Whitehead Institute, July 10, 1974 (Box 145)
      - "House Organ" proposal, request to other colleges for information about their in-house publication, September 11, 1974 (Box 145)
      - To Alumni September 13, 1974 (Box 145)
      - To High School Juniors, October 18, 1974 (Box 145)
    - 1975
      - President's Letter, February 27, 1975 (Box 145)
      - Fiftieth Anniversary of Duke, March 6, 1975 (Box 145)
      - University Letter, April 18, 1975 (Box 145)
      - Presidential Candidacy, May 20, 1975 (Box 145)
    - 1976
      - Response to Student Petitioners, RE: ITT Corporation's Operations in Chile and South Africa, December 20, 1976 (Box 145)
    - 1977
      - To the Faculty, October 14, 1977 (Box 145)
    - 1978
      - To Alumni, June 13, 1978 (Box 145)
      - To Freshmen, July 21, 1978 (Box 145)
    - 1979
      - Report of Scholarly Activities (No.1) January 1979 (Box 145)
      - To the Duke Community, RE: Equal Opportunity, January 9, 1979 (Box 145)
      - Report of Scholarly Activities (No.2) February 1979 (Box 145)
      - To Undergraduate Students, RE: Conduct at Basketball Games, February 20, 1979 (Box 145)
      - To Faculty, RE: Building University Center, March 1, 1979 (Box 145)
      - To Parents of Undergraduates (Tuition Increase), March 1, 1979 (Box 145)
      - To Duke Employees, RE: Job Families, March 26, 1979 (Box 145)
      - Report of Scholarly Activities (No.3), March 1979 (Box 145)
      - New Students for New Criticism (No. 1, Duke University Letters), April 23, 1979 (Box 145)
      - To Faculty, RE: Sanford Sabbatical, April 25, 1979 (Box 145)
    - 1980
      - Regarding Durham Progress Group, February 3, 1980 (Box 145)
      - To Faculty, RE: University Letters, April 29, 1980 (Box 145)
      - To Freshmen, August 1980 (Box 145)
      - To Duke Students, October 25, 1980 (Box 145)
      - To Parents, RE: Tuition Increase, December 30, 1980 (Box 145)
    - 1981
      - To Parents, RE: Summer Educational Program, February 18, 1981 (Box 145)
      - To Freshmen, RE: University Letters, June 13, 1981 (Box 145)
      - To Freshmen, RE: Code of Honor, July 4, 1981 (Box 145)
      - To Faculty, July 27, 1981 (Box 145)
      - To Freshmen, August 4, 1981 (Box 145)
      - Nixon Papers, Letter to Students and Alumni, August 18, 1981 (Box 145)
      - Nixon Papers, Letter to Academic Council, August 19, 1981 (Box 145)
      - To Students, RE: Directions for Progress, October 25, 1981 (Box 145)
    - 1982
      - Tuition Letter to Parents of Undergraduates, March 5, 1982 (Box 145)
      - To Seniors, May 4, 1982 (Box 145)
      - John Hope Franklin, May 9, 1982 (Box 145)
      - Wilson, Coach Shirley (Red), TS Statement top Alumni and Friends, December 6, 1982 (Box 145)
    - 1984
      - Avuncular Letter to Students, January 17, 1984 (Box 145)
    - 1985
      - To Alumni, January 4, 1985 (Box 145)
      - To Students, February 21, 1985 (Box 145)
    - 1986
      - To the Class of 1986 (3 letters) (Box 145)
    - 1987
      - To the Class of 1987 (Box 145)
      - On Summer Scholarship Program/Fund (Box 145)
    - 1988
      - To the Class of 1988 (Box 145)
  - Subseries 1.3. Inauguration, 1970, 3.0 ln. ft. (about 150 items (Box 146)
    Series consists of items collected during the inauguration of President Terry Sanford 18 October 1970 including a planning manual, programs, speeches, flyers, news clippings, greetings from other colleges and universities, a guest book, and color photographs.
    Arrangement: Unprocessed
- Series 2. Duke University. President Emeritus. Records 1985-1998., 24.0 ln. ft.(about. 20,000 items (Box 147-165)
  This series consists of administrative records, along with some personal papers. The bulk of material runs from 1992-1997 and consists of computer disks, correspondence, faxes, journals, mailing lists, memoranda, photographs, speeches, transcripts, website printouts, writings, clippings and other printed matter. The files are organized into subject files, correspondence (1990-1998), and writings.
  The records also include files on organizations to which Sanford belonged or boards on which he served. Included among these: Methodist College, Fayetteville, N.C. (Trustee); North Carolina Museum of Art (chaired Board of Trustees); Ovation, Inc. - a Fine Arts Network (Board of Directors); and the Sarah W. Stedman Center for Nutritional Studies (Board of Advisors). Some files continue and supplement material found in other series: American Dance Festival; Education Commission of the States; and Outward Bound.
  Files are included on courses Sanford taught within the Public Policy Studies Department at Duke from 1993-1997, most notably a course titled "Creativity in State Government". Syllabi, handouts, lists of students, and some correspondence are included. These files contain student identifiable data, and are subject to federal privacy legislation.
  The records show Sanford's continued interest in and opinions on various issues, including political ones. Examples include the Nicaraguan Canal project, poverty, and racism. Within the Racism file is a 1997 memo from Sanford to John Hope Franklin, Professor Emeritus of History at Duke University and chair of President Clinton's National Advisory Panel on Race, outlining his plans to begin an association to help promote improved race relations. Sanford mentioned National Good Neighbor Council as a possible title.
  Sanford's day-to-day activities during the 1990s are documented throughout these files. Folders labeled Journal contain loose-leaf paper with daily appointments and schedules detailing meetings, dinners, travel plans, and leisure activities. Often, Sanford would write notes on the particular meeting/event (wrote before and/or after). In 1993 Sanford kept a bound journal for a week in February. Other files documenting Sanford's daily activities include folders of telephone messages and two rolodexes of addresses and business cards.
  Other significant records include Sanford's Cyber Bookstore project. This was intended to create a means of purchasing publications over the World Wide Web similar to the Amazon.com. There are also reports, drafts, and proposals from the Ethics Review Commission of the United States Senate, 1993-1994, and files on his support for the Airborne and Special Operations Museum project in Fayetteville, N.C.
  Correspondents include President Bill Clinton, to whom Sanford voiced his opinion or expressed his support; and Howard Covington, Sanford's biographer. Sanford sent Covington thoughts or remembrances that he felt should be included in the biography, or he would write in response to Covington's questions. Among the recollections include a detailed account of Sanford's decision to endorse John F. Kennedy's presidential campaign.
  Two of the three boxes of writings consist of hand-written and typed drafts, research notes, a synopsis, and bibliographical material for Sanford's unfinished historical novel, Top of the World. Sanford worked on the novel from 1994-1998 and drafts of the first six chapters at the time of his death are included. According to an article in the Raleigh News and Observer (Jan. 10, 1994, p.3-A), Sanford did not think it would be completed until the 21st century. The third box contains drafts, notes, and additional material on three Sanford manuscripts. They include the unfinished works The Lasting Lyndon (1991) on the Lyndon B. Johnson administration, and Out of the Valley, (1975), surveying public policies; Sanford referred to the latter work as "an autobiographical political platform". The file also includes the manuscript of Outlive Your Enemies: (Commack, N.Y.: Nova Sciences Publishers, 1996), Sanford's study on aging and growing old gracefully.
  A final box labeled Miscellaneous contains primarily Democratic Party-related material from the 1980s and a note to incorporate them into the records.
- Series 3. Political Papers, 1965-1976
  The personal and political papers of Terry Sanford consist of correspondence, memoranda, manuscripts, newspaper clippings, reference material, printed matter, audiotapes, audiocassettes, videocassettes, and a scrapbook that document his personal and public life. Also present are correspondence, memoranda, clippings, speeches, statements, drafts, press releases, and printed matter documenting Terry Sanford's campaigns for the Democratic nomination for President in 1972 and 1976, including a large set of film recordings used for the 1972 campaign created by Drew Associates. Records documenting Sanford's study of the future role of state governments in society and in the federal system are present as is material concerning the Legislative Library Project. Sanford's work with the Democratic Charter Commission is also included.
  - Subseries 3.1. Personal and Political Papers, 1954-1985.
    The personal and political papers of Terry Sanford consist of correspondence, memoranda, manuscripts, newspaper clippings, reference material, printed matter, audiotapes, audiocassettes, videocassettes, and a scrapbook. The bulk were acquired from Sanford's house in Durham, N.C., and he apparently kept them close by for reference purposes for much of his career. Some folders appear to have been removed from his records as Duke President.
    The papers primarily contain the files of organizations to which Sanford belonged or boards on which he served. These included the Foreign Study League (advisory council); Citizens Committee for Government Reorganization (co-chairman); the National Council on Crime and Delinquency (chaired N.C. Committee); the National Municipal League/Citizens' Forum on Self Government (multiple offices including President); the National Public Affairs Center for Television (Board of Directors); the National Recreation and Park Association; National Urban League; Outward Bound; Shaw University (Trustee); the Soul City project; Southern Regional Growth Board; Robert Taft Institute of Government (Trustee); Children's Television Workshop; and Urban America, Inc. (Trustee).
    Also included are records from Sanford's political career and interests. Among these are records from his tenure as N.C. Governor, including files on race relations, reports, and correspondence; the 1960 Gubernatorial campaign; speeches and drafts; clippings and printed material; surveys of political climate and polls; the 1954 Senatorial Campaign (campaign manager for W. Kerr Scott); his support of Fritz Hollings' 1983-1984 Presidential Nomination; and correspondence with the N.C. Young Democrats, 1965-1968. Of particular note is a 1977 confidential memo that Sanford typed for his records recounting President Carter's request that Sanford accept the position of Ambassador to France. Other correspondents include Lyndon B. Johnson and John F. Kennedy.
    - Academic Freedom - Speaker Ban Law [1965-1966] (Box 166)
    - Addresses, 1973-1986 (Box 255)
    - Airborne, Five Hundred and Seventeenth (Box 166)
    - Associated Student Governments, 1968 (Box 255)
    - Beyle, Thad (Box 166)
    - Carneigie Commission on Public Television and Subsequent Legislation (Box 166)
    - Carter, President Jimmy (Box 166)
    - Center for Democratic Policy [1981] (Box 166)
    - Center for National Policy [1981] (Box 166)
    - Citizens Committee for Government Reorganization 1971-1973 (Box 166)
    - Coates, Albert, and Gladys, 1970 (Box 255)
    - Cochrane, William McW. (Box 166)
    - Compact for Education: S.A.S., 1965-1966 (Box 255)
    - Compact for Education, 1965 (Box 255)
    - Congressional Leadership for the Future (Box 166)
    - Correspondence, 1950s-1960s (Box 255)
    - Correspondence, 1950s-1960s; 2 folders (Box 270)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 270)
    - Correspondence: Campaign correspondence and other items, 196-1976 (Box 270)
    - A Danger of Democracy, 1981 (Box 270)
    - Daniels, Jonathan (Box 166)
    - Defense Advisory Committee on Women in the Service [Mrs. Sanford] (Box 166)
    - Democratic Policy Council (Box 166)
    - Democrative -- National Democratic Institute for International Affairs 1984-1986 (Box 166)
    - Durham City Club (Box 166)
    - Dykeman (Wilma) on Weatherford (W. D.) by Terry Sanford, 1966 (Box 166)
    - ESOPs/Kelso [Employee Stock Ownership Plans] (Box 166)
    - Education, Department of -- HEW Advisory Committee on Higher Education 1967- (Box 166)
    - Educational Television (Box 166)
    - Ehle, John, 1976-1986 (Box 191)
    - Elkins, Angie (Box 166)
    - Evans, Eli (Box 166)
    - Family Letters (Box 166)
    - Food Tax (Box 166)
    - Ford Foundation 1965; Carmegoe Corporation (Box 166)
    - Ford, Gerald R. (Box 166)
    - France (Box 166)
    - Giannini, Vittorio by John Ehle 1974 (Box 166)
    - North Carolina Court Reform (Box 166)
    - Governor of North Carolina -- Advancement School (Box 167)
    - Governor of North Carolina -- Association of the U. S. Army, Advisory Board (Box 167)
    - Governor of North Carolina -- Brewer.Burch/St. Hwy. Comm. Affair (Box 167)
    - Governor of North Carolina -- Chicago's War on Illiteracy (Box 167)
    - Governor of North Carolina -- Distinguished Citizen Awards (Box 167)
    - Governor of North Carolina -- Firemen (Box 167)
    - Governor of North Carolina -- Miscellaneous (Box 167)
    - Governor of North Carolina -- Public School Law, A Study of by Raymond Stone (Box 167)
    - Governor of North Carolina -- Race Relations (Box 167)
    - Governor of North Carolina -- School Bond Election (Box 167)
    - Gubernatorial Campaign 1960 (Box 167)
    - Gubernatorial Campaign 1960 -- Clippings (Box 167)
    - Gubernatorial Campaign 1960 -- Contributors (Box 167)
    - Higher Education (Box 167)
    - Higher Education -- North Carolina (Box 167)
    - Higher Education, Western Interstate Commission for (Box 167)
    - Hollings, Ernest F. (Presidential Nomination 1983-1984) [2 Folders] (Box 167)
    - Industrial Developers Association, North Carolina (Box 167)
    - Issues Committee 1975 (Box 167)
    - Johnson, Lyndon B. [and Mrs. Johnson] (Box 167)
    - Juvenile Courts & Correctional Institutions, Commission on, 1955 (Box 167)
    - Randall, George 1966-1968 (Box 167)
    - Kennedy, John F. (Box 168)
    - Lamar Society (L. Q. C.) -- State Planning (Box 168)
    - Lamar Society (L.Q.C.) (Box 168)
    - Miscellaneous, 1964-1969 (Box 168)
    - National Civil Service League (Box 168)
    - National Council on Crime and Delinquency - North Carolina Council (Box 168)
    - National Council on Crime and Delinquency, 1968-1969 (Box 168)
    - National Council on Crime and Delinquency, 1970-1972 (Box 168)
    - National Health Insurance, Committee for, 1970-1981 [2 Folders] (Box 168)
    - National Municipal League, 1969-1975 [2 Folders] (Box 168)
    - GWETA (Greater Washington Educational Telecommunications Association, Inc.) (Box 169)
    - National Municipal League,1976-1981 [3 Folders] (Box 169)
    - National Municipal League/Citizens Forum on Self Government, 1980-1987 [3 Folders] (Box 169)
    - National Programming Council for Public Television (Box 169)
    - National Public Affairs Center for Television (NPACT), 1971-1974 [merged with (Greater) Washington Educational Telecommunications Association (WETA) in 1973] [3 Folders] (Box 169)
    - National Recreation and Park Association, 1971-1974 (Box 169)
    - Governor of North Carolina -- North Carolina Fund (Box 170)
    - National Recreation and park Association, 1971-1977 [2 Folders] (Box 170)
    - National urban League, 1972-1975 [5 Folders] (Box 170)
    - North Carolina Bar Association, 1971-1978 (Box 170)
    - North Carolina Society to Prevent Blindness, 1979 (Box 270)
    - Outward Bound, 1966-1984 [2 Folders] (Box 170)
    - Paul Green Foundation (Box 170)
    - Personal (Box 171)
    - Political -- Small Investors Act, 1978 (Box 171)
    - Political, 1968 (Box 171)
    - Political, 1968 -- Brochures from the National Convention (Box 171)
    - Political, 1968 -- Citizens for Humphrey/Muskie - Staff (Box 171)
    - Political, 1968 -- Citizens for Humphrey/Muskie - TS Chairman of (Box 171)
    - Political, 1968 -- Democratic National Convention, Chicago, 1968 (Box 171)
    - Political, 1968 -- Democratic National Convention, Chicago, 1968 Clippings (Box 171)
    - Political, 1968 -- McCarthy, Eugene -- Letters Urging Support for (Box 171)
    - Political, 1970-1971 -- Referendum '70 (Box 171)
    - Political, 1974 (Box 171)
    - Princess Mother's Charities Fund of Thailand, Inc. (Box 171)
    - Prisoners (Box 171)
    - Professional Child Care Centers, Inc., 1971 (Box 171)
    - Salzburg Seminar (Box 171)
    - Sanford Appreciation Dinner -- Financial Records, 1964 [2 Folders] (Box 171)
    - Sanford Law Firm, 1970-1980 (Box 171)
    - Sanford-Jaycee Roast, 1981 (Box 171)
    - Save the Children (Box 171)
    - St. Phillips Community Kitchen (Box 171)
    - Terry Sanford, 1963-1980 (Box 171)
    - Terry Sanford, 1981 (Box 171)
    - Thank Yous (Box 171)
    - Scott, Mary K. (Box 172)
    - Scott, W. Kerr -- Senatorial Campaign 1954 (Box 172)
    - Shaw University, 1968-1976 [5 Folders] (Box 172)
    - Soul City (Box 172)
    - Southern Railway Syster, 1970-1977 (Box 172)
    - Southern Regional Policies Board [7 Folders] (Box 172)
    - State Programming for the 1970s, Institute on (Box 173)
    - Stein Library, 1970 (Box 173)
    - Swalin Book (History of North Carolina Symphony) (Box 173)
    - Taft, Robert A. -- Institute of Government, 1969-1983 [6 Folders] (Box 173)
    - Television -- Children's Television Workshop [2 Folders] (Box 173)
    - Transylvania University, 1978-1980 (Box 173)
    - "Beyond the Straw Men" (Tuition support in the North Carolina Legislature) (Box 174)
    - "Picking the President" -- Article for THE ATLANTIC, August, 1980 (Box 174)
    - "A Danger of Democracy" [3 Folders] (Box 174)
    - "Action by States Needed" (Article for National Civic Review) (Box 174)
    - "But What about the People?" (Box 174)
    - Manuscript [Notes for an abandoned book on Sanford's term as Governor] (Box 174)
    - Population Growth and North Carolina's Future (John E. Rockefeller, 3rd and Terry Sanford, 1982) (Box 174)
    - Publications by Terry Sanford (Box 174)
    - "Storm over the States" (Box 174)
    - Tobacco Road article (Box 174)
    - United Nations Association of the United States of America (Box 174)
    - United Natons, Implications of Space Communications of the (Box 174)
    - Unruh, Jesse M. (Box 174)
    - Urban Action Center (States) (Box 174)
    - Urban America, Inc. -- Merged with Urban Coalition to become National Urban Coalition, 1970 (Box 174)
    - Urban America, Inc., 1968-1970 [4 Folders] (Box 174)
    - Vietnam -- National Citizens Committee for the Amendment to End the War (Box 174)
    - Vietnam/Cambodia -- National Coalition for a Responsible Congress (Box 174)
    - WRAL (Box 174)
    - Wake Forest University (Box 174)
    - Walltown Charitable Community Center (Box 174)
    - War Committee, 1971 (Box 174)
    - Watauga Club (Box 174)
    - Wheeler, John H. Foundation, Inc. (Box 174)
    - Woodrow Wilson School Rockefeller Awards, 1968 (Box 270)
    - World Affairs, North Carolina Council on (Box 174)
    - World Peace Through Law Center (Box 174)
    - "You can't eat magnolias" (Box 174)
    - Young Democrats (Box 174)
    - Clippings (Box 175)
      - National Guard (Box 175)
      - Science and government (Box 175)
      - State finances (Box 175)
      - Vocational rehabilitation (Box 175)
      - Research Triangle (Box 175)
      - Local statements (Box 175)
      - Public welfare (Box 175)
      - National Governors' Conference, 1966 (Box 175)
      - Governors (Box 175)
      - Court and Bar reform (Box 175)
      - Highway study statement (Box 175)
      - Education: North Carolina Governor's School (Box 175)
    - Clippings scrapbook (Box 176)
    - Varmint dinner (Box 176)
    - Sanford current (Box 176)
    - New York Times supplement, 1961 (Box 176)
    - Sanford, Political, 1955 (Box 176)
    - Klutznik, Philip M. (Box 176)
    - Teaching Council (Box 176)